Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
This accident occurred to Lady Fuca because she was with child.
Now she has lost her child
while you just got pregnant.
I appreciate Your Highness's kind concern.
An innocent child has died.
Parents put their heart and soul into raising their child.
I couldn't bear to see another child die.
I hope your child will be more blessed by Heaven.
I thank Your Highness for your caring and compassionate words.
No, no. Please rise.
Since I am here, I have one more thing to say.
Cao Qinmo is even more difficult to deal with than Consort Fleur.
She "hides daggers behind smiles".
I almost fell into the traps she laid a few times.
If Consort Fleur is a fierce tiger,
Cao Qinmo is the tiger's sharp claws.
But as long as you know where the daggers come from,
you will be able to avoid them.
Standing in harm's way but not knowing who your opponent is ...
is the most dreadful.
Your Highness's health doesn't seen to be improving.
I know an imperial doctor.
May I introduce him to treat Your Highness?
Thanks for offering to help.
My health was damaged when I was young.
I feel really tired. I must go now.
I will ask my servants to go with Your Highness.
No one else should know.
Does the Emperor know about this?
I've sent the messengers.
I have instructed them to report in an unhurried and calming manner,
and emphasize Lady Sourire's pregnancy.
I hope he will feel less unhappy knowing Lady Sourire is pregnant.
I hope so, too.
His Majesty will find comfort in Lady Sourire's child.
It will help him recognize that other concubines will
also be able to carry imperial heirs.
There's nothing we can do about Lady Fuca's child now.
But nothing can go wrong with Lady Sourire's child.
Yes.
Imperial Mother, I have yet another thing to report.
What is it?
Consort Fleur wishes to see a doctor from outside the palace.
Why did she suddenly bring this up?
She has not been pregnant all these years
and thinks the imperial doctors are incompetent.
So she wishes to see a doctor from outside.
That was what she said in her request.
I heard Nian Gengyao approves the idea.
What do you think?
This would damage the reputation of the Imperial Infirmary.
I'm afraid it's not appropriate.
It's not.
But if her request is denied, she won't stop asking.
All right, we can arrange for a doctor's visit.
If it's a good doctor,
bring him here afterwards to check on Bamboo.
After serving me all these years, now she
has times when she feels unwell.
Yes, if Madam Bamboo is unwell,
it will be convenient for her to see a
visiting doctor during work.
Consort Fleur is right.
The doctors in the palace are just mediocre.
That's why people recover more slowly.
I'm exhausted. I need to rest.
Your Highness has a weak constitution.
Your Highness must be exhausted - exerting your mind and body all day.
If not for the tasks my mind desires to do,
I would have no reason to live in my debilitated body.
But Your Highness didn't have to go out on this cold and frosted night
and talk for so long with Lady Sourie.
All the children are innocent.
So are their mothers.
I cannot look on when she's in peril.
It's unfortunate that
I won't have a child in this life.
Your Highness, please stop eating.
Pickled cucumbers damage the Stomach.
Your Highness, please don't do this to yourself.
I vomited.
Song Zhi, I vomited.
Aren't you happy for me ?
Summon the imperial doctors!
Your Highness.
Lady Fuca was pregnant.
And Lady Sourire too.
They all can carry a child.
Why can I not?
Your Highness, you are young and it's just a matter of time.
I was pregnant before.
I had a boy.
It was because of her!
The medicine is bitter.
Having the sweet coix soup after will
soothe your throat and calm your mind.
Her Highness Consort Fleur.
Consort Fleur.
Your Highness, Consort Honnête has retired for the night.
Please visit tomorrow if Your Highness wishes to see her.
Out of my way!
Yes.
Keep her still.
Aye.
Your Highness.
How many years have passed
and you still storm into my palace like this?
How many years have passed?
Whenever I think of my unborn child,
how I wish I could eat your flesh and drink your blood!
Eat my flesh and drink my blood?
Isn't that exactly what you've been doing all these years?
How I wish...
I wish I could kill you with my own hands!
I am confined to bed by illness,
living a life that is no better than death.
Isn't that better than killing me?
Even if your life is no better than death,
it doesn't ease my pain of losing a child.
His Majesty didn't kill you, and after his coronation
he even promoted you to Consort.
How I hate you!
How I wish you can be made into a "human swine" and die!
Had I committed the unpardonable crime that you described,
His Majesty wouldn’t have let me live until this day.
His Majesty trusted you and protected you.
But I won't believe you even after I die.
You brought me that bowl of prenatal tonic.
You were the only concubine who stayed out of all
the rivalries and that was why I let my guard down.
I never imagined how vicious you were.
That you would poison me to abort my child!
My poor child.
He was a well formed boy.
And you killed him with your own hands!
You had no evidence and dumped all the blame on me.
You broke into my chamber and
poured a pot of boiled safflower into my mouth.
Yes, you lost your child.
But because of you I will never have children!
So what?
I hope your entire family will never be able to have children!
If you ever had any evidence,
you would have already "ground my bones and scattered my ashes".
There’s no need for wasting your breath standing here...
As long as you are still breathing in this palace,
we are not done with this!
Why does that even matter?
I have accepted my destiny.
My life has been ruined by your hands.
It’s late now.
There’s no good in disturbing the Empress Dowager.
Do you think I am afraid of that?
Of course you are afraid.
If Her Majesty finds out about this,
His Majesty will be told when he returns.
All these years, you have been continually in His Majesty's favor.
What you fear the most is the loss of his favor.
You're creating chaos tonight out of spite for Lady Fuca and Lady Sourire.
You resent them out of jealousy.
Aren't you afraid that His Majesty will be suspicious that
you were the one responsible for Lady Fuca's
miscarriage and Lady Sourire's injury?
You are welcome to wait and see
whether His Majesty gives priority to you or his children.
What happened to them has nothing to do with me!
That does not matter.
What matters is His Majesty’s judgement.
Just like when you were convinced that I had killed your child,
you would not believe the opposite.
Time passes slowly in the palace.
You will stew in your own juice.
I will take delight in seeing you "linger on your
last breath" while you wish you could die.
The Household Department will send no money to the Yanqing Hall.
All her stipends will be sent to the Imperial Infirmary.
That's to pay for her medicine.
Also, the Palace Laundry is not allowed
to wash clothes for her palace.
No fresh food will be sent to her palace.
Nothing!
Your Highness must not be angry.
It has always been done like that. Don't worry.
The imperial doctors are useless.
Send someone to tell my brother tomorrow
that I have Her Majesty's permission to see a doctor from outside.
Dr. Chen, I’ve heard that you are
the most eminent doctor across Qinghai.
What a blessing from Heaven that I have
this opportunity to meet and serve you!
Sir, I am flattered.
In the barren land of Qinghai, my only option
was to take up my family's medical practice.
I can’t hold a candle to the imperial doctors here.
I am vastly inferior.
I know nothing about medicine.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager kindly thought
you would want to exchange views with the imperial
doctors since you have travelled all the way to Beijing.
It would also benefit the people in Qinghai.
Her Majesty’s benevolent consideration is a blessing to thousands.
This way please.
Thank you.
Dr. Chen, I’ve heard that you’re here to visit Consort Fleur.
These are Her Highness’s medical records
since she entered the palace.
I hope this will be of help to you.
Thank you very much, head doctor.
Consort Fleur is a distinguished concubine
and in the highest favor of His Majesty.
That's why the Imperial Infirmary pays
particular attention to her.
More than twenty doctors have visited her for pulse diagnosis.
They are all nationally renowned doctors.
Yes, General Nian also repeatedly impressed upon me
the paramount importance of Her Highness’s diagnosis.
I’m really nervous.
I can understand.
I'm fortunate to speak with you beforehand, doctor.
Otherwise, I would be trembling with fear.
There you go.
Have you been serving my brother all along in Qinghai?
Yes.
For how long?
I've been the General's doctor since he moved to Qinghai.
Qinghai is an undeveloped land.
You made a contribution to my brother’s good health.
Song Zhi.
I thank Your Highness.
A hundred taels of silver does not look heavy.
But they can still kill a person if thrown upon his head.
If you can restore my health, even ten thousand taels
will be an insufficient reward.
But if you cannot,
I will still reward you ten thousand taels ...
for your funeral.
I beg Your Highness to spare my life.
I dare not withhold my efforts.
Rise. I like to make things clear in advance.
I will certainly give you what you deserve if you do your utmost.
How is my health? Am I able to conceive?
Your Highness is in good health.
If so, why haven’t I become pregnant again?
Is it because of the miscarriage I had?
It has been a few years since the miscarriage.
It should no longer have any influence.
Otherwise, the imperial doctors would have noticed.
Pregnancy comes from Heaven's blessing and the right effort.
But most importantly, the right time.
I beg Your Highness’s pardon,
but has Your Highness been very eager for a conception?
Of course.
That's it.
Eagerness is not good for a conception.
An eager heart makes it harder.
When Your Highness calms your mind,
it will happen immediately.
Are you referring to …
Mood. You are pushing it away with an eager heart.
You mean, I’m still able to carry a child?
Your Highness is deeply blessed.
All you need is good timing.
Timing is important but we can't just sit and wait.
Prescribe me the best medicine.
Yes.
Take those silver ingots with you.
Two thousand taels will be delivered to your residence later.
I humbly thank Your Highness.
You may raise.
I thank Your Highness.
Doctor Chen, is everything all right?
The weather is not hot today,
Why are you sweating so much after
visiting the Palace of Earthly Honor?
I am abashed.
The palace of the imperial family inspires awe in my humble mind.
Dr. Chen, if you are not in a rush,
would you mind checking on a maid who serves the Empress Dowager?
I am flattered to obey. Please lead the way, sir.
Dr. Chen, can my illness be cured?
Madam, you are in good health and not sick at all.
No, I've already seen the imperial doctors.
They all said it would take a long time for me to be cured.
If a person is not ill but everyone around her says she is.
What would happen if you are the only one
that speaks the truth, Dr. Chen?
I ...
On the contrary, if a person is ill
but no one dares to speak of it,
and only you noticed and spoke out, Dr. Chen,
what would happen?
Then everyone would think I have gone mad.
They would, despite having been a renowned doctor all your life.
But... besides myself,
there would still be other imperial doctors.
What if they revealed the truth?
It is not possible; it will never happen.
The entire Imperial Infirmary "speaks with the same tongue".
Then ...
Then I will also "speak with the same tongue".
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Majesty.
You're finally awake.
When did Your Majesty come back?
I didn't even hear you.
I heard about the incident that befell you and Lady Fuca while I was in Henan.
I was very concerned.
So I came back as soon as things were properly dealt with.
Your Majesty has endured a long journey.
You should have rested at the Hall of
Mental Cultivation before visiting me.
I wanted to see how you are.
Lady Fuca had a miscarriage.
I've lost another child.
Why ...
Why is it so difficult for my children to survive?
Si Lang, you are tired.
You should get some rest here.
You must safely give birth to this child.
I will love him and cherish him.
Your Majesty, don't look at me like that.
I look so ugly with my wounds.
Don't worry, I will make sure the imperial doctors heal the wound.
How about the injury on your arm?
It's all right.
That was silly of you.
Even if you were not pregnant,
what if you hurt yourself trying to save Lady Fuca?
I was not saving her.
I was saving an imperial heir.
Even though she was carrying an imperial heir,
she still cannot compare to you in my heart.
I understand that
you and your father are upset about what Consort Fleur did.
Don't worry. I won't let you down again.
It was not something I could control.
I appreciate Your Majesty thinking of me.
But since your father has been appointed to be a supervisory official,
now he can rightfully report on anyone's misconduct.
I have told the Empress that
you will be promoted to Concubine on
the day of Consort Estime's promotion.
I won't let you suffer any more injustices.
I don't feel there was an injustice.
When all of this is settled,
our child will be born.
I will then promote you to Consort
and build a new palace for you.
The Palace of Pearl Jade is good for me.
And I do not care about the titles.
I just want a peaceful life
with Your Majesty and our child.
- Spring.
- Mr.Su.
Are you here to deliver the decree, sir?
It's not dusk yet.
Is Her Majesty inside?
Yes, I'll go inform Her Majesty.
Thank you.
Your Majesty, Mr. Su is here.
We were just saying
His Majesty visited only the Palaces of Earthly Honor and Pearl Jade after returning.
It turns out His Majesty was intending to
visit and stay with Your Majesty.
Today is the 15th, night of full moon.
His Majesty must be thinking of Your Majesty
so he sent Mr. Su here early.
That's enough. Show him in.
Yes.
Please come in, Mr. Su.
Peace to Your Majesty.
You may rise.
Why has His Majesty sent you over?
His Majesty wishes to inform Your Majesty that
he will not come to the Palace of Great Benevolence today.
On the fifteenth of each month,
His Majesty always visits Her Majesty.
What's going on today?
Did Consort Fleur invite His Majesty for dinner?
Or he is feeling unwell?
His Majesty said since Lady Sourire just got pregnant,
he went to visit her immediately after finishing with state affairs.
Your Majesty can rest early tonight.
Certainly.
Lady Sourire is smart and sweet-natured.
She always understands His Majesty's heart.
His Majesty should spend more time with her.
Spring.
Yes.
Select a pair of Hetian jade ruyi from the storehouse
to place on Lady Sourire pillows to wish her good sleep.
Yes.
Allow me to take my leave, Your Majesty.
You may go.
It's still early.
Your Majesty should rest in the Palace of Great Benevolence.
It's all right.
Your Majesty should not miss the night of
full moon with Her Majesty because of me.
I want to stay where my heart is
on any night.
But Her Majesty has always been good to me.
I don't want to make Her Majesty upset.
All right then. I'll have breakfast with her tomorrow.
Your Majesty.
It's sour.
Sorry, I hadn't tasted it. I didn't know it was sour.
Your Majesty shouldn't have more.
It's very sour. But, don't discard it.
Send them to Lady Sourire.
Her appetite has changed. She loves sour food now.
An appetite for sour food signifies it's a boy.
Lady Fuca has lost her child.
And Lady Sourire just got pregnant.
You must take good care of them.
Certainly.
It's Lady Sourire's first time being pregnant.
She must be taken special care of.
That's for sure. She can't be like Empress Première.
My sister had a tragic fate.
I won't let history repeat itself.
You should not only take good care of her,
but also take precautions.
What happened to Lady Fuca ...
It was my lack of care.
You must do all you can to prevent that.
Remember, cats are no longer allowed in the palace.
Yes.
Also, Lady Sourire's promotion
ceremony must be carefully prepared.
It will dispel the bad luck in the palace.
I understand.
Her promotion ceremony will take place in two days.
Is everything ready?
Lady Sourire is now a proper concubine.
and will have a formal ceremony.
If only we had a few more days to
adequately prepare for her promotion.
I need nothing more.
I will entirely obey Your Majesties.
You don't have to stand.
I know you are always thoughtful.
Even though we don't have more time for the preparation,
we have to follow the proper procedure.
Don't worry, Imperial Mother.
I have taken care of everything.
But a new ceremonial robe could not be made in the limited time.
So I asked the Ministry of Rites to alter the robe that
Consort Estime used for her Concubinary Ceremony.
That's an expedient solution and yet appropriate.
You've done well.
Spring-bloom.
Yes.
That hairpin looks so familiar.
It looks like the one Your Majesty
awarded Lady Vertu when she was pregnant.
You have such sharp eyes.
The Emperor was angry and tossed this hairpin onto the floor.
The hairpin was damaged at the top.
I have had it repaired with a ruby.
The design is of the Two Gods of Harmony. I wish for you to have it.
Come here.
It looks very good on you.
Sadly Noble Lady Vertu did not
have Heaven's blessing to wear it.
May you accumulate Heaven's blessings
and carry more children for the Emperor.
I thank Your Majesty.
What are these?
They were sent by His Majesty.
This is the Jade Dew Salve.
It's said to be the most effective for scar removal.
This is the Jade Repair Powder.
To reduce the redness.
His Majesty has also awarded other medicine like these.
The scratch was not deep.
But it's still dreadful to look at.
From now on, you have to be
extra careful about everything, My Lady.
I will also pay special attention to your food.
His Majesty has also sent a cook from the
Imperial Kitchen to prepare all your food.
No one else can lay a finger on it.
Dr. Zhang will be responsible for your medication.
He is an experienced and respected doctor.
I do not believe he will make any mistakes.
My Lady, Attendant An is here.
Show her in please.
Yes.
Sourire.
I hope my voice does not startle you.
I know I shouldn't go out when I'm sick.
What happened to your voice?
Have a seat.
My cough hasn't gotten better. My voice is affected.
Why are the doctors so useless?
Why didn't they treat you carefully?
The doctors wouldn't prescribe strong
medication because of my fragile health.
I managed to accompany Her Majesty to appreciate the flowers that day.
I was shocked by what happened to Lady Fuca.
The stress also aggravated my condition.
That's why I couldn't come earlier to congratulate you.
That is nothing compared to your health.
Is His Majesty aware?
I was summoned once to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
But I couldn't sing.
His Majesty told me to have a good rest.
Since then I haven't see him again.
I didn't know.
When did that happen?.
It's not something that I would want people to know.
I talked too much. I made you feel bad.
It's not the reason for my visit.
Has your wound got better?
It is healing.
The doctors have seen it.
And His Majesty granted some medicine.
I think I'll be fine after a few days.
The medicines from His Majesty are good.
But certain herbs can't be used when you are pregnant.
Also, most of these medications are probably tributary offerings.
They might not be suitable for your constitution.
You are right.
Here.
I have this Scar Relief Gel which is a family formula.
The formula was said to have cured
King Sun He's beloved consort Lady Deng
when she was hurt by a jade ruyi.
It contains peach blossoms and pearl
power to brighten your complexion.
Fish bone gelatin and honey smooth your skin.
Fine powders of jade and amber can
heal the wound and remove the scar.
The most precious ingredient is the white otter marrow.
It fades the scar and restores your skin to pristine condition.
The white otter marrow is terribly rare.
I doubt there is much of it even here in the palace .
That's right.
The white otters are found along the Fuchun River.
The marrow is usually extracted from the
rarely-found bone remains of dead white otters.
It is best when the marrow is fresh.
Otherwise, the medicinal effect is greatly reduced.
It smells so good.
I would usually perfume it with spices.
But I thought they would not be good for you when you are pregnant.
So I used fresh flowers instead.
This way it does not smell like medicine.
This is extremely good medicine but too costly.
I shouldn't accept it.
Whatever I have is yours, Sourire.
I'll feel relieved to see your wound healed.
Besides, in the springtime,
there is more dust and pollen in the air
which can negatively affect your wound.
The gel should not be exposed to wind.
You must cover the wound if you go out.
That's very considerate of you.
Words cannot describe how grateful I am.
Try this.
I hear that your mother can visit you
and accompany you during childbirth.
Is that true?
Yes, His Majesty will grant her permission to come
to the palace when I'm eight months pregnant.
You are always cheery day and night;
when did you start to sigh?
I haven't seen my mother for so long.
You are so lucky, Sourire. You can see
your mother when the baby is bigger.
You are two years younger than me
and the youngest child in your family.
And you haven't seen your family ever since you moved into the palace.
You must miss them so much.
It's all right, Attendant Chun. Your family will be happy
knowing your life in the palace is good.
Besides, the food outside cannot compare to what we have here.
These are freshly made milk and water caltrop cakes.
It tastes the best when it's just out of the steamer.
Ummm, so good!
How I envy you!
You can always toss your worries out of the clouds when you see food.
I've read in books that one's heart and mind follow innate purity.
That is probably how you would be described.
I don't care about purity.
When the food is good, my heart will follow.
I heard from Mist that you like water caltrop cakes.
so I told the kitchen to make some for you with milk.
The milk makes it more fluffy.
The cake is much better than what we have at home.
I'll tell the kitchen to make this everyday if you like.
But remember, don't overindulge yourself.
Sourire,
is there really a baby growing in your belly?
Yes.
But he is so small that he might not even have hands or feet yet.
Really?
If you like him, he will be your nephew.
Really? I will be his aunt?
Yes.
This is my deposit
for him to be my nephew.
Since I have received your gift, I can't renege on it now.
How nice your aunt is to you!
She has already sent her gift before you are born.
Nephew, grow up quickly.
When you grow up, I will give you all the delicious food in the world.
Taohuaji cakes, rice cakes, red bean rolls, and pickled lychee.
I'll never say you can't have them.
You will be a plump child.
And your aunt is going to have so many
children so you will have friends.
Are you happy about that?
Sourire, stop teasing me!
Attendant Chun goes like the wind.
Sourire, how about I have seven or eight
kids to play hide-and-seek with him?
Is that enough?
That's enough. They will be a lot of work.
Your Highness, Dr. Jiang Chen and
Dr. Jiang Shen were here for a routine visit.
But they were informed that His Majesty is coming for lunch
and it would be improper for them to be here.
So they said they will come this evening.
By the way,
His Majesty still visits the Palace of
Pearl Jade a lot even though she's pregnant.
Ask Dr. Jiang to advise His Majesty not to.
Even though Lady Sourire is now pregnant,
there's also that little vixen Attendant Chun.
It's lucky for her that Sourire cannot serve the Emperor overnight.
What a bewitching young girl!
She acts innocent and plays dumb to gain His Majesty's favor.
Your Highness must not be angry.
She is nobody in the palace.
She is ill-mannered
and Your Highness will be able to find a reason to remove her.
Madam, you are well respected in the palace.
I am distinctly honored to have you
arrange my hair for the ceremony, Madam.
My Lady, your hairline is high.
Of all the concubines I have served,
you have the tallest.
Now that you are with child, My Lady,
it shows you have great blessings from Heaven.
No one else is comparable.
Exactly. Everyone knows that the higher
one's hairline is, the more blessed they are.
It's evident that you are greatly blessed, My Lady.
Ah, it's so heavy.
If you think this head ornament is too heavy,
what happens when you become a Noble Consort?
Stop it!
Vermilion is right.
If you give birth to a prince, My Lady,
there will come a day when you become a Noble Consort.
Consort Estime from the Feng family;
Concubine Sourire from the Zhen family.
By the grace of Heaven's decree to the palace,
may you bring virtue to yourselves and peace to the imperial harem.
May you diligently serve His Majesty and expand the imperial family.
We are delighted to obey advice from Your Majesty.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
email: carsenwei@yahoo.com
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.